Today's Sutta is Samyutta Nikaya
636.
>> [clears throat]
>> Says um
thus I've heard, one time the Buddha was
staying at
Kukkutarama monastery in the city of
Patil Pataliputra. Yeah.
Pataliputra. Yeah.
Uh at that time the world honor one
addressed the because I should explain
to you the cultivation of the four
establishment of recollection.
What is the cultivation of the four
establishment of recollection?
And um
And the Buddha said
that when a Tathagata and Arhat a
perfectly awakened one
accomplished in knowledges and conduct,
well gone, knower of the world,
unsurpassed guide of persons to be
trained, teacher of the gods and humans,
Buddha world honor one appears in the
world, he proclaims the true Dharma
excellent in the beginning, excellent in
the middle, excellent in the end, good
in the meaning and good in expression,
pure and complete, revealing the
Brahmacariya, the holy life.
A young man of good family or a young
woman of good family hearing the Dharma
from the Buddha gains pure faith.
Having cultivated in this way, seeing
the faults of the household life with
its desires and pleasures, seeing the
bondage of the defilements, they delight
in solitary dwellings.
They leave home
to practice the path no longer
delighting in the household life.
Dwelling in homelessness, they aspire to
complete purity and undertake the
perfect and stainless Brahmacariya for
the whole life.
They think
I will shave off hair and beard, put off
on the saffron robe, and out of faith go
forth from the household life into
homelessness to practice the path.
Having thought this, they abandon wealth
and relatives, shave off their head and
beard, put on saffron robe, out of faith
go forth into homelessness. They
straighten their bodily conduct, guard
speech from the four faults, and purify
their life, purify their livelihood.
>> [clears throat]
>> They practice the noble precepts, guard
the sense faculties, and protect the
mind with right recollection. Um
When the eye sees form, they do not
grasp the general appearance nor their
particular features.
If dwelling with the eye faculty
unrestrained, worldly desires and
distress and unwholesome states flow
into the mind
then they cultivate the proper
discipline regarding the eye faculty.
In the same way, they cultivate proper
discipline regarding the ear, nose,
tongue, body, and mind.
Having uh perfected the noble precepts
and well guarded the sense faculties
in going and coming, looking and
turning, bending and stretching, in
wearing robes, carrying the bowl, in
eating, drinking, chewing, tasting,
walking, standing, sitting, lying down,
falling asleep, and walking
twice in speaking and remaining silent,
they dwell clearly knowing and fully
aware. >> [cough]
>> [cough]
[clears throat] >> Um
>> Um
Having perfected Having perfected such
noble precepts, guarding the sense
faculties, possessing the right
recollection and right knowing, they
dwell secluded and ease in solitude.
They sit alone in an empty place, at the
root of a tree, or in a quiet dwelling.
They straighten the body, establish the
recollection before them, and compose
the citta.
They abandon worldly desires and
distress. Free from sensual desire, they purify
Free from sensual desire, they purify
the mind of sensual desire. They abandon
ill will, sloth and torpor, restlessness
and remorse, and doubt, so the five
hindrances. Uh free from ill will, sloth and torpor,
Uh free from ill will, sloth and torpor,
restlessness and remorse, doubt, they
purify the mind of these states.
Thus they abandon
the five hindrances that corrupt the
mind, weaken the wisdom
obstruct progress, and do not lead to a
Nirvana. Having abandoned these five hindrances,
Having abandoned these five hindrances,
they dwell contemplating the body in the
body internally, ardent, clearly
knowing, mindful, having subdued worldly
desires and distress.
Uh
In the same [clears throat] way, they
contemplate the body externally,
internally, and externally.
So, likewise with feelings, with citta
and dhammas, internally, externally,
internally and externally, ardent,
clearly knowing, recollected, having
subdued worldly desires and distress.
Um This because is called cultivation of
the four establishment of recollection.
So, and when the Buddha had spoken thus,
the because rejoiced in his words. So, um
So, um
yes, it's not like a long Sutta and
obviously um you can see the a certain
amount of of kind of um parallels and
similarity with the with the common Pali
passages such as
uh you know, gaining faith initially on
account of that person leaving the
household life and so on.
Um obviously [clears throat] what's
interesting here as as we're going to
see through when we go through the
questions I I I kind of asked
is that um
well, the whole kind of four
establishment of recollection, the
Satipatthanas uh are clearly described as a
uh are clearly described as a
as a very kind of a um
encompassing process, so to speak
that um pretty much starts by leaving
the household life.
So, it's far from uh
uh a retreat technique that you could
just adopt on top of your existing life
values and behavior
but it's the beginning of says what is
the cultivation of the four
establishment of recollection? It's when
the Tathagata arises in the world and a
young man or a woman hear the hear it
and they gain faith in his teaching.
Um and that that is actually I think um
found in Pali not like uh this
explicitly, but it's in combination I
think it's some Anguttara Nikaya,
shorter Suttas.
Um where it's said that pretty much
there is no uh it's not possible to see
body as body internally, internally,
externally, or both if one is not living
Brahmacariya withdrawn from worldly
desires and um
afflictions. So, um
So, um
this Sutta in that regard just kind of
reiterates all those scattered
statements throughout Pali Nikaya.
Um so, yeah, Satipatthanas begin pretty
much by
uh
undertaking the training in virtue
correctly. So
So
having cultivated this way, seeing the
faults of the household life, in other
words, what Pali Sutta say, seeing that
the household life is crowded, dusty,
overwhelming hard to maintain certain
hard to maintain certain
uh standards and training in that regard
cuz it's just the environment, it's not
meant for it.
Um that's why they would see the bondage
and the defilements and start to delight
in solitary dwellings and and um
uh abandoning it all.
Um so, um the um
Yeah, rather than being kind of going
through the Sutta technically and um
explaining the stuff that's self-evident
I thought of um um
well, discussing those kind of more like
uh um
practical questions
that a person, whether householder or a
monk can can still use like today
can can still use like today
to actually assess and re-evaluate and
reflect on the practice at whatever
stage they are in, so to speak.
So
as I said, yeah, technically speaking
the observing body in the body in the
Satipatthanas are towards the end of the
Sutta uh after the whole training in virtue,
uh after the whole training in virtue,
sense restraint, uh abandoning the
desires and the and the
and the griefs of the world.
Um but as I said, from from a certain
angle you could say, well, that's
already the beginning of Satipatthana
cuz it all leads to the discernment of
uh the citta, the body for what it is,
not as a as a as a kind of compilation
of
uh sensations and other externally
observed sense objects, but the actual
internal counterpart, you know, like the
the empty village, the the all the
similes in the Pali
that takes time and withdrawal to
develop. So So
like
when you like read the Sutta now and you
ask yourself, okay, so what is
mindfulness? When I if I say
mindfulness, mindfulness, what is
mindfulness? Sati. Let's not even
translate it. Let's just say, what is
Sati? Um ask yourself that question.
Um ask yourself that question.
So, what what what
what would you answer? What is Sati? I
mean, obviously you'll you'll give some
you might be giving some learned answer.
Well, Sati is recollection or it's this
and comes from the root of that word,
but like for you
here and now
if somebody were to ask you what is Sati
and you were to describe it, what
phenomenon, palpable phenomenon, in your
experience here and now
would you be referring to?
What is it? Like
when you say Sati, what is the actual
phenomenon that you are designating?
And uh
you should be clear on that. So, that's
the point. It's like
um you might have as I said the a
semi-accurate idea of what Sati is on
account of learning and practice and so
on
but when you say Sati, even say if you're
when you say Sati, even say if you're
not explaining it to anybody else when
you say ah Sati I should I should
practice mindfulness. What specific
phenomenon are you referring to?
What sums it up? What is its essence of
the Sati practice? Let's put it that
way. So
So
is it is it something that you do? Is it
like a
>> [clears throat]
>> like a technique that you go through a
certain set of motions or or or verbal
kind of cues that bring it up?
Or is it something you just directly
kind of say access
recollect, reestablish?
Either way
what is it in and of itself? What is
Sati? Like like for you how do you see
it? So that that's a useful um
So that that's a useful um
thing to ask yourself.
Like and even if by the way if it feels
clear you should be checking in every
now and then because it might get
obscured. Because
uh
what tends to happen practically
speaking is that okay you develop as I
said some semi-accurate more or less
doesn't matter idea of Sati.
Um that is a kind of a a a summary of
everything you learned, everything you
tried, you know, a bit of right, a bit of wrong
you know, a bit of right, a bit of wrong
and so on.
And you're operating under that
imperative of I must be mindful and do
this uh practice that kind of contains a
certain degree of as I said moving
complexity and moving parts of Sati
practice like this in this scenario
doing this body in the body breathing
there but it's like but it's not seen as a
but it's like but it's not seen as a
single unifying phenomenon that
reestablish everything correctly pretty
much instantaneously when reas- when
recollected or when when put forward. Uh
whichever way you would choose to
translate the uh body mukam from the
from different sutas.
And that's why it's important to to
dwell on this.
Again, you're not looking for a for a
pleasingly theoretical all-encompassing
answer that would that would cover all
angles. You you you're actually looking to see
You you you're actually looking to see
that phenomenon that you're talking
about when you say yeah mindfulness or
Sati or recollection or recollectedness.
What is it? Like like when I say that
what am I thinking of?
Do I see that clearly? Um
Um
and you start questioning that and then
you'll see there's going to be a lot of
layers to it.
Because that's why it can be obviously
>> [clears throat]
>> very misleading as well.
Uh like I have no doubt that people
without prior restraint and without
simply simplification of the life that
they sort of list as a prerequisite to
any practice of Sati
they would still have some notion of
Sati. It's not like an entirely divorced
It's not like an entirely divorced
concept that they cannot even fathom
unless they're sat in bed and practice
like no they can and that's the problem.
It's whatever level of that phenomenon
you can fathom, whatever idea you get
unless you're told that it won't be the
Sati you need to aim for it will be the
Sati for you so you won't be looking
further. You will think oh that is the
Sati because again it matches what the
Suta says. Oh yeah it's recollection
embodying the body. So so it's not
too difficult to to wrap your head
around these practices but it's it's it's
these practices but it's it's it's
difficult to not fall into a trap
whereby you stop recognizing
or at least questioning whether there is
more in it.
And obviously there is more in it. You
know, if people start actually studying
the whole body of the sutas and the
agamas and so
a clear picture emerges of you know how
far you need to go and what you need to
look for but as I said before most
people would not necessarily undertake
the level of that of that that kind of
study and practice but it will more
likely coming across the sutas here and
there in second-hand accounts
uh and then very easily falling into the
idea of oh yeah practice of mindfulness
and recollection I know what it is
because they do know what it is
at that time to that extent at that
level. But if they were told to then also
But if they were told to then also
question it like oh but is that it? What
is it specifically that I'm referring
to? Not just a like as I said a
combination of kind of semi-techniques,
ideas, theories, a bit of prac-
informed by some practical attempts.
Like no no no specifically when I say
Sati what what is it? What state of mind?
what what is it? What state of mind?
What attitude towards the mind I'm
referring to like in its kind of essence
without any secondary psychologizations,
rationalizations, explanations or or or
secondary cues.
So that's why it's like a
>> [clears throat]
>> once you start questioning it
and as I said you're going to start
discovering layers and layers to it.
Well one of the most obvious layers
>> [clears throat]
>> that that will be revealed
is the is the layers that that that or
dimension that gets revealed
when you undertake uh
celibacy or restraint or practice
towards it. In other words when you
start containing your worldly desires
not blindly following, certainly not
justifying them through your views.
Saying oh there's no harm in sensuality
I can handle it. So even if you are say
not able to give them up you're at least
on the level of views
maintaining the recognition that they're
unbeneficial uh obstructing um hindering and taking
uh obstructing um hindering and taking
you away from the goal. So
So
if you start training in that direction,
start containing your desires, start uh
practicing sense restraint, containing
of the animal well that's
[clears throat] when you recognize that
whole new real so to speak dimension of of
new real so to speak dimension of of
Sati that that that that kind of brought
into play. They didn't exist before but
obviously you cannot know or reference
what doesn't exist for you in the
beginning. That's kind of the point. Why it's like
That's kind of the point. Why it's like
you need to be doing it to see that
there is more to it.
And many sutas list those uh similes
many similes that they explain exactly
this. Um so it's like a
Um so it's like a
that's why the whole
um
Brahmacariya surmounting worldly worldly
desires, worldly worries uh basically
entanglement with the world. So that
that needs to be the first point of
practice of Satipatthana.
Of the noble eightfold path or whatever
>> [clears throat]
>> whichever way you want to designate it
it has to begin by approximating the
Brahmacariya life.
So whether you're a householder or a
monk that
training in in virtue, sense restraint,
guarding of the sense doors, subduing
worldly desires and distress I eat the
level of involvement, intentional
involvement with the world
is the first step of Satipatthana. Is
how you practice it.
>> [clears throat]
>> So it's like if your practice is not
there yet that you could sustain that
type of lifestyle
well you have a work cut out for you.
Start working towards it gradually as I
said increasing saying no to the desires
of the unwholesome, unbeneficial kind
until the mind will not be
um overwhelming you with panic, despair,
anxiety, worry at the mere uh thought of
saying no to your sensual desire.
Cuz you know as the other Suta says like
initially when when a person not versed or trained
when when a person not versed or trained
in Dhamma hears about sense restraint
and saying no to their sensual and
sexual desires it feels like a sudden
abyss, sudden precipice. Like everything
was fine and suddenly you just reached
the cliff. That's how quickly that that
that dread arises.
And that's normal. It's like
that just shows you the state of the the
the wilderness of that animal. Like
okay. So instead of despairing on
account of it or trying to like as I
said um
um
rationalize it away through through
whatever views and stances and
justifications you take it on as a measure of what
you take it on as a measure of what
needs to be developed. Okay now
>> [clears throat]
>> when I think about sense restraint, when
I think about approximating Brahmacariya
in a daily life and beginning the actual
practice of Satipatthana correctly
according to the sutas and agamas
>> [snorts]
>> my animal freaks out.
Citta just just freaks out. Okay. So
it's obviously
too much too soon but the direction
remains outlined so let me begin slowly
building it up
and making it sort of become used to it.
Because again the only reason it's a
sudden precipice is cuz the whole
direction has been ignored and pretended
it doesn't exist.
So that's why approximating Brahmacariya
in daily life doesn't mean like
overnight you need to become perfectly
celibate and meet all the requirements
but it means you need to start working
towards it.
Bit by bit wherever you are recognizing
the excess the uh un- unnecessity uh of
your intentional, volitional
intentional, volitional
engagement with centrality proliferation
well you start curbing it. You start
saying no. You start enduring bits and
bits of those of the of the upsets and
panics and little abysses
that your animal will be coming up with
until it comes down because again the
only reason it it feels so like powerful
and overwhelming is because
it's a new thing. It just hasn't been
presented before, and obviously
capturing a wild animal suddenly will
obviously reveal how wild it is and how
much it resists and hates it, but
eventually comes down. So, that's kind
of the point. So, you would be closer to
practicing Satipatthana correctly by
training in virtue and
properly gradually [clears throat]
developing sensory strength than by not
doing that or doing it conditionally for
with an expiry date for 10 days or 2
weeks or something.
Uh knowing that you would go back and
the meantime do all these techniques of
of body scanning and whatnot, which has
nothing obviously to do with the actual
practice of Satipatthana that the suttas
describe as the one way only that leads
to purification.
So,
yeah, so that I addressed that one
basically. >> [clears throat]
>> [clears throat]
>> Yeah, so like there's a there's a thing
that occurs a number of times in the
sutta and Pali as well mentions I think
kind of
if I remember Pali mentions um
the equivalent of subduing worldly
desires and distress.
I think he mentions it as something
that's already been done
in the in the Satipatthana suttas
basically or suttas that mention
Satipatthana it was always mentioned as
having dealt with that, having abandoned
worldly joys and worries or something like that.
joys and worries or something like that.
I forgot the common translation.
He then dwells peaceful, withdrawn here
and now.
Um this agama is kind of nice cuz it
includes a bit of a bit [clears throat]
of nuance in between
whereby before a person is
a monk or anan is is dwelling happily in
seclusion purifying the mind from
unwholesome states, they are making the
effort subduing worldly desires and
distress. In other words,
In other words,
you trap the animal,
the worldly desires, the desires of the
prior access to the wilderness and
things that were causing you joys,
happiness, worry, or distress will keep
coming up.
So, how how do you go about subduing it?
So, that's the question again.
>> [clears throat]
>> Can be another reflection you ask
yourself every now and then.
every now and then.
Um
say you live withdrawn
to
the best extent you're able to at the
time from unwholesome uh
unbeneficial desires and pursuits and so
on, but obviously, you know, the the untamed
but obviously, you know, the the untamed
mind still comes up with pressures,
desires, distress.
So, how are you subduing that?
What does that mean?
Does it mean
hypnotizing the mind to the point of no
thoughts coming up? It's peaceful cuz
it's asleep.
But is that truly a peace?
Again, take the simile of the of the
wild animal that you're taming.
Um
does the real peace come when animal is
just temporarily asleep?
Or would the real peace come from when
animal is incapable of attacking you
regardless of whether it's awake,
sleeping, agitated, or not? Which is the
actual more
foundational peace?
>> [clears throat]
>> Obviously, when the question is asked
like that, you already know the answer.
And that's kind of the point.
It's not like that you shouldn't be
trying to like, well, calm down the
animal if it helps.
if it helps.
Uh you'll be doing it whether you want
it or not one way or the other, but you
should certainly not fall into view that
artificially calming down the animal
because it just scares me too much is
the way of practice. No.
Teaching the animal, making it
understand these things
that you emulate through your own
behavior and right choices by body,
speech, and mind, that is what will
calm it, actual samadhi, actual samatha,
whereby doesn't matter [clears throat] what
doesn't matter [clears throat] what
state
>> [cough]
>> the animal is in
because you know that it cannot turn
against you because it has been
sufficiently tamed.
So, that's what the subduing of worldly
desires and distress has to pertain to.
So, when things concerned with the
world, desires and so on, yes, you say no to
desires and so on, yes, you say no to
the outpour through your behavior. So,
you don't act out by body, by speech, by
mind, but that's not where it ends. It's not
but that's not where it ends. It's not
like now you just spend time wishfully
thinking that the animal will never
remember again those things that used to
um
spur desires in it or distress. No, no,
no. You go, "Okay, so there is no acting
You go, "Okay, so there is no acting
out. I've contained the animal.
Now I actually have to uh
reflect on these things correctly, bring
them up, bring their counterparts up,
broaden the context. So, when those
thoughts do pop up, which they
inevitably will,
>> [clears throat]
>> they won't limit the mind anymore in the
sense they used they won't be
immediately called
inflict kind of narrowing of the focus
of the animal. In other words, they will
be less and less of a trigger. So, it's
still the same thing.
It's still the same provocation,
but comes with a different background.
That's that whole
um [clears throat] talking about, you
know, the context, the broadening of the
context, the right perceptions, bringing
them up in a controlled
um suitable
um
virtue-based environment
so [clears throat] that animal relearns
to not just immediately fall for the
trap, but
not lose the sight of the broader
picture even when it's the most
triggering things that come up.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, then another
um practical thing to consider would be
like when the sutta talks about the
faults of the household life.
Again, not as a
>> [clears throat]
>> theoretical answer enumerating all the
correct things, but more like for you.
So, and by the way, again, this need to
be household life, any current
situation. You going to have a degree of
You going to have a degree of
distraction, compromising choices. It's
just like to what extent do you allow
that do you allow that to go?
So, faults of household life could be
faults [clears throat] of my current
situation that are kind of self-inflicted, so to
that are kind of self-inflicted, so to
speak. So,
you look for the moments where you're
giving into hindrances,
comfort, forms of entertainment. Not So, again,
forms of entertainment. Not So, again,
you're not judging or trying to get rid
of the existence of those things or
possibilities, but you're trying to see
when your choice takes you there.
So, when you willingly choose to go
there. So, when you willingly choose to give in
So, when you willingly choose to give in
to unnecessary excessive comfort or like
food or entertainment,
um
when you're delighting in socializing,
even if it's on the basis of
obligations, for example, I have to, but
it's like, "Okay, but are you doing it
cuz you have to?"
Or "I have to" becomes a permission for
"I can
carelessly uh engage with this because it has to be
uh engage with this because it has to be
done and stuff like that.
So, all you need to do is as I say, keep
an eye on your choices.
And when the choice is clear whether
you're choosing that, you don't choose
it. Why do those things come up on their own
Why do those things come up on their own
and how often that becomes irrelevant.
That's why the whole point is like you
don't have to be fighting everything all
the time, everything and nothing. You
just need to recognize when the choices
are clear, and again, they have to be
clear cuz whenever you're making a
choice means there is a consciousness of
choosing. So, there is the options that
you are aware of. Otherwise, the choice
would be making a choice would be
incomprehensible. It would be
inconceivable. So, that's why the the the the choosing
So, that's why the the the the choosing
is that kind of a um
point of convergence, so to speak.
Um and that's what you need to keep an
eye on. That's where the faults become
faults. That's where hindrances become
hindrances, when you choose to take them
up.
When you choose to act out of them.
And again,
people keep choosing
>> [snorts]
>> not because they didn't have sufficient
amount of special novelty hypnotic
experiences in their meditation or
revelations, it's because they haven't
really thought about this frequently
enough. They haven't trained these
reflections in order for them to sink in,
in order for them to sink in,
to become, as I said, the informing
context behind quick triggering desires,
hindrances, and so on.
That's why again, you know, the the the
so many suttas talk like frequently
recollecting and
um dwelling on the suitable themes that
would then be resulting in dispassion
and so on. It's not a it's not like a
like a magical resolution, but it's just
training and effort and and and
diligence, really, nothing else.
So, it kind of ties in with the whole
idea of guarding the sense doors.
Again, you don't have to be a
a monk or anan in order to guard the
sense doors.
Um you can already be doing it. So, how
do you guard the sense doors?
Do you guard the sense doors after you
chose to allow senses to look, smell,
taste, touch unsuitable things?
Or is guarding of the sense doors done
before that?
So, do you first give in to the
unwholesome choice and then try to
repair it. Or are
Or are you able to not even give in to
the unwholesome choice and then there is
nothing to repair?
Obviously, I already gave an answer now,
but the point is not the answer. The
point is do you bring those questions to
yourself as often as possible?
as often as possible?
That should be your meditation. And then
start painting the bigger picture bit by
bit. Every time you you you start these
reflections, you bring these questions
that I keep sort of listing and creating
that revolve around the same things but
give you different angles,
you are adding to your canvas of that
context. You are adding bit by bit, like
no masterpiece is painted overnight. So
it's just like but it grows, that's the
point. It adds more. What you've been
questioning before, part of it becomes,
as I said, embedded in that context now.
So next time you add more and more and
you don't have to keep revisiting
everything from the start cuz as I said,
it becomes part of that background that
it's informing your current experience
more and more accurately, so to speak.
That's pretty much how you would be
developing the right view as well.
Um
so then
say a person does this, practices
questioning, then the the whole place for seclusion.
then the the whole place for seclusion.
We spoke about it in other videos, so um
I won't go into too much detail on that
here, but uh
let me just Mhm.
Just checking if the zoom's still on.
The uh
so the seclusion
uh
to whatever extent you're able to
have, say, periods of seclusion,
re-evaluate re- you should re-evaluate
as to like can you improve it?
In other words,
are there choices concerning my, you
know, life, current living situation,
duties, and so on
that I could
reorient, so to speak, so that
I have more seclusion for the practice. Because
Because
probably yes, for most people,
especially in a household life, that
could be improved. As for the monks,
nuns, you realize
um
as I said,
you it can always be improved, not
necessarily like you need to find a new
place or something, but you would see
that there it is going to be at least some
there it is going to be at least some
degree of your intentional involvements
or engagements that uh would be taking
you away from seclusion.
I'm just speaking broadly, obviously.
It's up to every individual to to to to
assess that cuz obviously like seclusion
in and of itself, it's not going to have
a magical results either. So you need to
be
doing things rightly, practicing things
rightly where seclusion can then be the
actual useful thing.
Um but yeah.
Re-evaluate at the end of your day
uh when there were no, say,
uh extracurricular activities that you
had to attend,
uh monastery projects or, I don't know,
family visits in a household life and
stuff, just reassess whether your choices are
just reassess whether your choices are
aligned with maximizing seclusion that
you can get.
Again, not for
sleeping or distracting yourself, but
for these these right practices, right
reflections, right contexts.
Whether you spend that seclusion
walking, hiking, sitting, studying the
suttas, doesn't matter. It can be
different times on different days, but
like are you physically alone?
Just you and your own mind, basically.
Um
if a good part of your day, you could
say, "Yeah, I'm in most of it is in
seclusion." Then you don't have to worry
too much or micromanage now every choice
you make, "Oh, I shouldn't have talked
about that because, you know, 5 minutes
longer or something, I could have had
my" That's like, you know, becoming a
bit precious and irrational about
seclusion. Um seclusion just means
Um seclusion just means
um
time when the work and reflection
is most efficient.
I mean, if if you don't have seclusion,
you can still do the work. It's just not
won't be as efficient.
So
you need to recognize that. It's not
like, "I can only practice when I'm in
seclusion. If there's no seclusion,
there is no practice." I mean,
householders became anagamis in the
suttas with their duties and families and
with their duties and families and
things they had to look after. So
you know,
obviously means they had to make more
effort that would have been a lot more
efficient if they were not householders,
but the work is work, needs to be done and
the work is work, needs to be done and
like, you know, I don't know, stuff can
happen and you end up hospitalized or in
a in environment where you simply cannot
practice seclusion no matter of choices,
right choices that you make.
Are you ready to practice in that
environment? Or is your idea of practice just
Or is your idea of practice just
completely kind of merge with seclusion,
without seclusion, it's just there is no
practice. Everything I do then must be
simply about bringing me back in secu-
bringing me back into seclusion where I
can practice. That's not an accurate
idea. So seclusion is is a is a is a certainly
So seclusion is is a is a is a certainly
a very, say, useful
prerequisite, but it's a relative thing.
Because the obvious seclusion that
physical seclusion would be leading to
is seclusion from unwholesome states.
Seclusion from greed, aversion,
distraction, but you are not united with
greed, aversion, distraction through
presence of other bodies and people and
sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches.
You are united through your own ignorant
choices towards those things.
So physical seclusion can emulate the
separation, but as we already, I think
we did it in in these studies as well,
the actual seclusion, the only way to
develop it is from the inside, the
withdrawal. So that's exactly how uh householders
So that's exactly how uh householders
became anagamis. Like overcome sensual
desire, the five hindrances, the the
the the sorry, the five lower fetters.
While not being as secluded as monks,
not even having an option to be so.
But yet they made the effort, applied
the the the the effort where it matters.
So internally they have uh secluded
themselves from the hindrances, from the
from the hindrances, from the
unwholesome states
to the point of where certain views and
assumptions in regard to centrality of
will just
were evaporated, were destroyed.
And that kind of ties in with this with
the with a kind of follow following up
follow follow
following point,
which is the practical ways of
addressing the five hindrances correctly
throughout the day. That's exactly it.
So
whether you're secluded or not, as I
said, seclusion is an added bonus, but
if whatever things come up
that prevent your seclusion, do you then
justify your annoyance?
Do you feel righteous in your ill will
because somebody has interrupted your
all important seclusion? Or do you take
that interruption of seclusion as the
practice to not give in to the five
hindrances? Again, you have a choice what you're
Again, you have a choice what you're
going to emphasize.
The world, the concern with the world,
which becomes seclusion is another
concern with the world,
or the internal giving in to the five
hindrances in this instance would be
irritation and ill will.
>> [snorts]
>> Um so then another kind of useful
reference point, but again, I mean, I
asked this I I added this to the end of
the the self-questioning cuz
the self-questioning cuz
people can easily fall into technique of
body watching and scanning. So it's
say you are reflecting correctly,
you are making
the beneficial choices, saying no to the
unbeneficial choices, containing the
animal to the best of your ability,
while you're doing that, which is, you
could say, the meat of the practice of
the right practice,
um
how often or are you
uh simultaneous to whatever you're
rightly practicing,
are you simultaneously aware with simply
the state of your body as a whole in
your situation? So
is it seated? Is it walking? Just like
do you see it as a as a like say,
you're bringing up like this now, what
we spoke about seclusion. So you're
you're you're making sure you don't fall
into a trap of becoming precious about
seclusion. So you're bringing up
scenarios, you're reflecting, you're
seeing if the animal becomes triggered
on account of things he doesn't like.
You see, do you like allow it in a sense
of like, "Oh, yeah, yeah, and I should
have done this." Like, "No, no, hold
on." Anything, everything can be a basis
for the right practice if the right
effort is made correctly.
>> [snorts]
>> So while you're doing these reflections,
do you also
in that whole package, so to speak,
see yourself seated on a chair in your
room while thinking these things? Again,
don't mystify too much,
but don't completely exclude it either,
those recognitions.
Cuz basically those indirect ways,
uh should I tell you that now?
It might just become another technique
people seek.
Anyway, I'm qualifying it now. So make
sure it doesn't become another of you
seek. Um,
basically those indirect ways
when say you are
enduring things rightly, not giving into
sensuality, training in virtue, guarding
of the sense, those indirectly seeing
your body in those situations is the
most accurate way of seeing the
phenomenon of Kaya. It's not when you
are directly attending it or feeling it
or body scanning it and stuff.
But obviously, see
trying to directly attend to those
indirect ways of the way the Kaya is
recognized can start to emulate the indirect way,
can start to emulate the indirect way,
but it's actually rooted in your direct
attention of gaining that
mindfulness of the body or whatever you
think it is.
So, that's what I'm saying. The only way
Well, the most accurate way of practicing
the most accurate way of practicing
mindfulness of the body is when it's
genuinely indirectly seen in regard to
whatever say you are rightly preoccupied
with. So, it's training that indirect
So, it's training that indirect
peripheral
uh, and making sure that it doesn't
become your
as I said, covertly direct way of
indirectly peripherally seeing it cuz
you think it's a magical method for some
purification. No, magical method method
for purification is making the right
choices throughout your day
when there is greed, non-greed, you
choose non-greed, aversion, non-aversion
you choose non-aversion, distraction,
non-distraction you choose
non-distraction by body, speech, and
mind. To the best of your abilities, the
more you do it
the clearer it will become what needs to
be done.
So, the kind of last point is is like after
the kind of last point is is like after
you know, everything we said
uh, when you think or when you hear uh,
when you think or when you hear uh,
continuous uninterrupted mindfulness
Sati um, that you know, even the Suttas
um, that you know, even the Suttas
mention
what does it mean to you? What What What
do you think that is? And I ask that
because again, like despite
>> [laughter]
>> everything we say and even people that
say actually listen and think about
these things
when you hear about continuous
mindfulness, you still might think it's
like oh, it's like a continuous focus of
non-interrupted pristine awareness of
the pure consciousness of the eternal
chitta, whatever.
It's like this kind of
full laser beam focus all the time
omniscient in every direction, but it's
like is it?
You know, after everything we said the
Agamas and these Suttas and that Suttas
and and when we listed, you know, how
Satipatthana is practiced, is that what
continuous uninterrupted mindfulness
would be? Or not?
So, like sit with that question. What is
the continuous uninterrupted
mindfulness? Is it based on my determination to
Is it based on my determination to
keep it fo- keep my focus aligned?
>> [snorts]
>> Or is it a an effortless result
of doing things the right way?
Training the right way.
Which one is it? Again, obviously I'm
answering it because it's not about
specific answer oh, it's this or that.
It's more like s- asking [snorts]
yourself to see where your implications
rest. Do you still expect uninterrupted Sati
Do you still expect uninterrupted Sati
to be as I said, like um, uninterrupted
uninterrupted
beam of awareness that that that
instantaneously sees everything all the
time as as it comes and it goes?
Or do you think continuous mindfulness
is basically where emphasis emphasis
cannot be
reshifted back onto back onto
desire
ill will
sloth laziness
restlessness as in those things will come up
as in those things will come up
but they don't shift the weight back
onto them to become the center of your
experience. They remain as something
that has come up, but contained.
Because that continuous mindfulness
does not require
you actively holding [snorts] it
together. Cuz that's obviously you won't be
Cuz that's obviously you won't be
mindful of that.
That's obviously narrowing of the
perspective.
So, it's it's it's good to ask these
things because like you know, everybody
you're going to have some preconceived
notions hiding here and there, little
expectations that as I said would be
fueling certain expectations and modes of
certain expectations and modes of
behavior that
the only reason they do so cuz you never
really stopped and questioned them. It's
like hold on, I'm still acting as if I'm
supposed to be
you know, mindful like uh,
um, in every direction omnisciently all
the time in regard to everything, but
that that can't be the case.
If mindfulness is is is developed on
account of Satipatthana begins with
training in virtue and sense restraint
I mean, that already is not something
I'm doing all the time. I'm doing it when
doing all the time. I'm doing it when
the choice to go that way or not present
itself. I'm choosing rightly. I'm enduring the
I'm choosing rightly. I'm enduring the
state of the animal that comes up as a
result of that choice. I'm not giving
in. Wait for it to calm down. I present it
Wait for it to calm down. I present it
with the right perceptions. So, it's
like Oh, so that's really the mindfulness
Oh, so that's really the mindfulness
when that
an extent of the context has been
developed sufficiently
whereby even without any effort from
your part to bring the right context and
contain the animal, the animal doesn't
go back there because as I said, the the
the the big picture that you painted now
is clear as the day and whatever pops in
the front, the animal cannot not see it.
So, that's the uninterrupted continuous
mindfulness. It's the result of the of
of building up the right practice.